Finding Aid for Shepard family papers, 1807-1934
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Shepard family papers 1807-1934
Shepard family.
85540 Aa 2; UAx; UAm
John F. Shepard family; diaries, photographs, recipes and correspondence concerning family matters and nineteenth century farm life; also professional correspondence, student notebooks and lecture notes of John F. Shepard.
3 linear feet
1 folders
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received from Arthur Shepard (donor no. 4361 ); additional materials came from Alfred C. Raphelson (donor no. 4549 )
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The Shepard family came to the Midwest from Malone County, New York. The family settled for a time in Greenfield, Illinois where John F. Shepard was born on January 30, 1881. After attending Greenfield High School, Shepard entered St. Lawrence College in 1897 and was graduated with a B.S. degree in 1901. He began graduate study at the University of Chicago the following year, but transferred to The University of Michigan in 1903, with appointment as Assistant in Psychology. In 1906, he became the first student to receive the Ph.D. degree in Psychology at this university and was then appointed Instructor. In 1909, he married Berenice Barnes of Marshall, Michigan, who died in 1952. He was promoted to the rank of Assistant Professor in 1911, Associate Professor in 1915, and Professor in 1918.
In 1914, the Regents appointed Shepard inspector and advisor to the architect and building committee for the construction of the Natural Science Building. He also advised with the Librarian on the construction of the University Library building. He was so effective in this capacity that in 1921 he was appointed by the Regents as Supervisor of Plans, which position he held until 1925. During his tenure as Supervisor of Plans, besides several additions to existing structures, the following new buildings were completed: Store House Office building, Store House and Shops Addition, Clements Library, East Engineering Building, University High School, Angell Hall, East Physics Building, Law club, Couzens Hall, East Medical Building, and the University Hospital.
During World War I, Professor Shepard was a member of the Committee on Classification of Personnel in the Army War Department. He held membership in the American Psychological Association, the Research Club of which he was secretary for three years, the Society of Experimental Psychologists, and Phi Beta Kappa. He served as president of the Michigan chapter of Phi Beta Kappa in 1938-39 and as President of the Michigan Chapter of the Association of University Professors in 1939-40. He was given the honorary degree of Doctor of Science from St. Lawrence College in 1925.
Professor Shepard served on the College Executive Committee from 1936 until 1939 and was Acting Chairman of the Department of Psychology for the first semester of the academic year 1940-41 and again for the years 1943 to 1945. He retired from the University at the age of 70 on January 30, 1951. He died in November 1965.
Although the Shepard family papers (1807-1934) cover three generations, the bulk of the materials are from John F. Shepard. The earliest correspondence is primarily addressed to his father Arthur, and to his grandfather John from family members and relatives. The letters deal with health, crops, and relatives. There are also letters from John F. Shepard's wife Berenice to her mother Mary Barnes (maiden name Van Valin) and from Berenice's father Charles to her mother. The Barnes and VanValins lived in Marshall, Michigan.
The John F. Shepard papers include professional correspondence from 1911 to 1934, mostly relating to University building plans. There are also minutes (1921-1925) of the Committee of Five on the Comprehensive Building Program, as well as Shepard's student notebooks from philosophy and psychology courses taught by James R. Angell and James H. Tuft at the University of Chicago, and by Alfred H. Lloyd and Walter B. Pillsbury at the University of Michigan.
The photographs are mainly of his wife's family, many from the late nineteenth century.
Subjects:
Agriculture--Michigan.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Cookery.; Farm life--Michigan.; Marshall (Mich.); University of Michigan--Buildings.; University of Michigan. Committee of Five on the Comprehensive Building Program.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Psychology.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Children.; Classrooms--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Families.; Minges, Abram, 1818-1908.; Minges family.; Musicians.; Shepard, John Frederick, 1881-1965.; Shepard family.; Soldiers--American.; Van Valin, Amos.; Van Valin family.; Women.
Contributors:
Shepard, John Frederick, 1881-1965.
Genre Terms:
Albumen photoprints.; Ambrotypes.; Diaries.; Drawings.; Photographs.; Tintypes.
- Family papers
  - Correspondence
    - 1807-1845 (Box 1)
    - 1846-1865 (Box 1)
    - 1866-1868 (Box 1)
    - 1869-1870 (Box 1)
    - 1871-1875 (Box 1)
    - 1876-1877 (Box 1)
    - 1878-1880 (Box 1)
    - 1881-1900 (Box 1)
    - 1901-1910 (Box 1)
    - 1911-1915 (Box 1)
    - 1916-1925 (Box 1)
    - Undated (Box 1)
  - Family diaries (Box 1)
  - Family recipes (Box 1)
- John F. Shepard papers
  - Professional correspondence
    - Undated and fragmentary (Box 1)
    - 1911-1960, 13 folders (Box 1)
  - Committee of Five on the Comprehensive Building Program
    - Minutes 1921-1925, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Miscellanea, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Student notebooks (University of Chicago), 5 volumes (Box 2)
  - Student notebooks (University of Michigan), 6 volumes (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook of newspaper clippings concerning University of Michigan building programs circa 1921-1923 (Box 2)
  - Lecture notes for course in Systematic Psychology 1939-1940, 2 volumes (Box 2)
  - Draft of writing: Studies in the Circulation and Sleep (Box 2)
  - Newspaper articles in support of John F. Shepard's pro-Soviet attitudes (ca. World War II) (Box 2)
- Photographs
  - Children (Box 2)
  - Groups (Box 2)
  - Identified individuals and groups. Includes: Alice French, Elijah Lester, Eliza Lester, Abram Minges, Frank Minges, Olive Eugenia Minges, Orlow Minges, Theda Minges, Walter Robb, and Annie Van Valin (Box 2)
  - Men-larger photos (Box 2)
    (includes photo of musician)
  - Men-smaller photos (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Women-larger photos (Box 2)
  - Women-smaller photos (Box 2)
  - Tintypes
    - Little girl with necklace (Folder UAx)
    - Women, children, groups (all unidentified): (Folder UAx)
    - Portraits, 9 items (Folder UAx)
    - Men (all unidentified): (Folder UAx)
    - Portraits, 8 items (Folder UAx)
      (include photos of soldiers)
    - Man in high silk hat (Folder UAx)
  - Portrait of Amos Van Valin, charcoal drawing (Folder UAm)
  - Group portrait including Berenice Barnes Shepard, Marshall, Michigan 1900 (Folder UAm)
- Research materials
  - Notes and other materials on maze experiments (Box 3)
  - Digests of John F. Shepard's course notes (prepared by graduate students) (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous manuscripts (Box 3)